[seagulls crying,
waves crashing]
Poor girl.
Yeah.
Bruising and abrasions
on the neck suggest
some sort
of physical attack.
That's why
they called us in.
- No clothes, no I.D.?
- Nothing.
Doesn't look like she was
in the water for long.
Contact the coast guards,
see if they've had
any distress calls
or missing person reports.
Yeah.
There's the guy
who found her.
William Gardiner.
He saw the body
from up on the bluff.
- 'Mr. Gardiner?'
- Thank you, sir.
I'm Agent Lisbon.
You wanna tell me
what happened?
I was coming
to check on the monarchs.
Butterflies.
He runs a sanctuary.
I was up there.
Where he's standing,
the man in the suit.
[male #1]
Hey!
[whistles]
- You with the police?
- 'Yes, I am.'
[snorts]
Patrick Jane.
Jed Stack.
This is my land.
Hey, Jed.
There's a dead woman
on the beach in Wracker's Cove.
Yeah.
Well, who is she?
Don't know.
Any idea?
No.
How would I know?
Eh, your land.
I thought
maybe, uh, your body.
That's absurd.
Sorry. I'm just pokin' at ya.
It's often instructive.
Why don't you come meet
my colleagues?
[horse blusters]
This is Jed Stack.
Agent Teresa Lisbon.
Agent Grace Van Pelt.
This is Jed's land.
How do you do, ma'am?
Ma'am.
Mr. Gardiner,
what are you doing here?
I found her.
I was checking
on the monarchs.
Butterflies.
Yes. I saw some.
You were trespassing.
For God sakes, forget about
your property rights for once.
A woman's dead.
The woman's death has nothing
to do with your trespassing.
So she's on your land?
No. Strictly speaking, my land
ends at the high-water mark.
She's on state land.
But given the location
perhaps she's a tenant
or an employee of yours?
I have no tenants,
and I employ no women.
And besides, she was obviously
washed up by the sea.
She must've drifted over
from the mainland
or fell off a ship.
Nothing to do with me
or my ranch or this island.
It seems to make sense.
Nice to meet you, Mr. Stack,
and, uh, butterfly man.
- Gardiner, yeah?
- Yes.
Neither of you were
born here, were you?
No.
What's that got to do
with anything?
Nothing. Just lucky to live
in such a beautiful place.
So, Mr. Stack..
[instrumental music]
[grunts]
Good idea.
We'll see.
Beautiful, isn't it?
For a crime scene. Yeah.
[theme music]
[Cho]
Dental records
just came in.
The victim's Talia Suarez,
19 years old.
Raised in
the foster care system.
Check with family services. Find
out what they know about her.
Rigsby and Van Pelt
are on their way.
Is there anything on
the coast guard front?
They've had no reports
of anyone missing overboard.
What about the mainland
across from the island?
We've got local PD canvassing
all the marinas,
hotels, and motels along that
stretch of coast. Nothing yet.
- Alright. Keep me posted.
- Where are you going?
Back to the island.
The island? Why? If her body
came from the mainland--
Jane's got a theory.
Right.
Ah.
Nice. It's not
what we're looking for.
You could make
a necklace out of it.
I could.
You should. You should have
some kind of restful hobby.
I don't see it.
Hard to believe the moon
causes tides, isn't it?
I mean, we all know it does,
but it just seems so unlikely.
I guess. I've never really
thought about it.
That's 'cause you're
a city girl.
A-ha!
My theory made concrete.
I told you.
Yes, you did.
I thought I saw
a tea shop in town.
I could use a cup of tea.
What about you?
You need a hand with that?
[Patrick]
'I can manage.'
[exhales deeply]
[rattles doorknob]
Uh.
Uh. Well, that's disappointing.
It's closed.
Picturesque, isn't it?
In a desolate sort of way.
Where are all the locals?
Good question.
[cell phone rings]
Cho.
Coroner came back
with a preliminary report.
Larynx was crushed
by a blow or heavy pressure.
'No water in the lungs.'
So she didn't drown.
Dead before she went in.
Also, physical evidence
indicates
she was sexually assaulted
before she was killed.
'Was there any DNA recovered?'
'Yeah, but no matches
in the database.'
Check out the background
of the men on the island.
'See if any of them have
a history of sexual assault.'
See you soon, I hope.
Just like the tea shop.
There's nobody here.
- Where is everybody?
- It's intriguing.
A mass vanishment.
That's not even a word.
Well, it's been known
to happen.
Roanoke colony. The Olmecs.
[Lisbon]
Hello? Hello?
I know where they are,
Lisbon.
I can picture them gathered
together in a dimly lit room
plotting their mysterious
island purpose.
That's really creepy.
Relax.
Talia Suarez. Mm.
Yes, uh, we were hoping
you could tell us--
Murdered, huh?
That's too bad.
But then, deadbeat kids like her
nearly always end up badly.
"Deadbeat kids like her"?
Oh, we see it all the time.
She was sent to us at 6.
Mother died of a drug overdose.
Father murdered.
Oh, and a problem
from the first.
Insubordinate, argumentative,
resistant to authority.
It's a long list.
Pretty girl, looked like.
Vivacious, but no discipline.
No common sense.
What about her foster parents?
Can we talk to them?
Didn't have any.
Kept running away from
the homes we placed her in.
Ended up finishing her time
in a group home.
Can we get that number?
Maybe there are friends
we can talk to.
I'll, uh, see what I can do
and get back to you.
You know, the truth is,
some of them..
[lowered voice]
...you just can't help.
[clicks]
[dials]
Thanks for your time.
Hey.
You know we're never gonna
hear from her again.
Not since you knocked
her coffee over her desk.
She wasn't gonna
do anything to help us.
It's a tough job.
Maybe she's doing her best.
She puts in her 20 so she
gets her pension. Pisses me off.
- I noticed.
- I do my job.
You don't hear me complain.
Why can't others do theirs
so maybe a kid
doesn't have to die.
Alright. I'll drive.
Gimme the keys.
That's alright.
I wanna drive.
I don't think so.
Give me the keys.
- What's with you?
- You're worked up.
I should drive,
so gimme--
- Cut it out..
- Give me the keys.
- Come on. Just--
- What's the matter with you?
Okay. No problem. You drive.
Now two additional
ferry crossings a weekend
during the summer months
equals a 35% increase
in revenues projected.
Now, I don't understand
how anyone can be against that.
The runoff from Stack's
cattle ranch
is already affecting
the groundwater pH balance.
- Another thing that you--
- Point of order, chair.
- I had the floor.
- Oh, now, Peter.
- Let's not be so fussy.
- Excuse me for interrupting.
I'm agent Teresa Lisbon
from the CBI.
And this is my colleague,
Patrick Jane.
I'm sorry, but we're
in the middle of a meeting.
- Can you come back later?
- No, we can't.
A woman was murdered here.
We're here to discover
who did it and why.
Her name was Talia Suarez.
Can any of you
remember seeing her?
[Peter]
- 'Sir.'
- Mm?
- Wasn't she found on the beach?
- Yes.
Well, I mean,
that would indicate
that the tide, uh,
brought her in, surely.
That's mainland business.
Yes, we have nothing to do
with happens on the mainland.
Messy place, the mainland.
That's why you're all here.
To escape from all that,
and of course, she's from there
because no one here
knows her, right?
That's right.
There's a lot of flotsam
that washes up
on San Felix all the time,
doesn't it?
- Certainly.
- Mm-hmm.
Summer weekends, the harbor
gets all sorts of trash.
[sighs]
Especially after storms, yes.
Excuse me. If you would?
Thank you.
So here's your island. It's a
beautiful island, I must say.
Here's your harbor, on the
leeward side of the island
closest to the mainland coast.
And the body was found
in Wracker's Cove
which is here, I believe.
On the western side of
the island.
The furthest side
from the mainland coast.
Now, I would think
it would be difficult
for a body to drift from here
against the currents
and the prevailing winds,
to here.
Another compelling fact.
If you throw something
into the water in Wracker's Cove
it will drift out
to sea for a bit.
And then, it will come
back to shore.
I checked with this.
Talia Suarez died here.
So look to your neighbor
and think
'how well do you know them?'
Because someone on this island
committed murder.
[crowd murmuring]
We'll be back.
I've been doing my best to track
Talia after leaving foster care.
- And? Anything useful?
- A series of minimum wage jobs.
She never stayed longer
than six weeks at any one.
- Moved all over the state.
- What else? Friends?
- Acquaintances?
- Nothing yet.
I talked to employers.
They say she was a good worker.
- Kept to herself.
- What about family services?
They're no help either.
It's sad, boss.
We're the only ones
that care about her.
Keep looking.
There's footage of her getting
on the ferry to San Felix.
- No camera on the island side.
- Uh, what's this?
Police sent it over.
Talia's room.
Beachfront motel
on the coast
'across the strait
from San Felix.'
Toothbrush, toothpaste,
a change of clothes?
That's it?
- That and a notebook.
- What notebook?
Jane's got it.
It's a diary of sorts. She wrote
letters to her dead parents.
That's sad.
Then there's this, I found
tucked away in the back pages.
"San Felix fish." Mm.
Does this seem
too easy to you?
Only one way to find out.
Who's in charge here?
We ain't open to tourists.
[sniffs]
Crab.
You can't be out here
for safety reasons.
We're with the California Bureau
of Investigation.
We need to ask you some
questions, mister...
Lafleur. Jack Lafleur.
So what's this all about?
I don't think you're gonna want
to talk to us out here, jack.
Uh, is there somewhere
a little more private?
Get back to work.
Let's go to my office.
So what's this all about?
Tell me about Talia Suarez.
What? Who's Talia Suarez?
The girl we found murdered
in Wracker's Cove.
What's that got to do
with me?
We found this in her diary.
That doesn't make any sense.
Ah, there we are.
Hey, hey. Those are mine.
[papers rustling]
This is impressive.
Is that a new dock?
No, uh, a pier. Wait.
A wharf.
Would you call
that a wharf?
It's big.
I'm expanding my business.
I need more room.
Look, I got no idea why
some girl wrote
whatever she wrote,
but I never heard of her.
You're barking up
the wrong tree.
Maybe it was somebody
who works for you.
We've been out at sea for the
past week. We just got back.
I told you,
it doesn't make sense.
Even if this girl of yours did
come here, we were all gone.
Your murder's got nothing
to do with us.
It's a pretty airtight alibi.
Yeah. Dock's interesting,
though.
It is?
Well, the Pacific Ocean's
been horribly overfished.
No fisherman these days needs
to build a larger dock.
You think that has something
to do with the murder?
Yes. No.
Not necessarily, no. Maybe.
I just think
it's interesting.
Or not. Let's go talk
to the rancher.
[Lisbon]
Whoever put Talia Suarez
in that cove
had to have carried her
across your property.
[Jed]
'My ranch is 300 acres, and
Wrackers cove's on the far end.'
You could carry a passel load of
bodies without anybody knowing.
What brought you to the island?
Who are you running from?
- What?
- Mm?
I wasn't running
from anybody.
Only I look around this room,
I see horses and cows
but I don't see
any friends or family.
No kids. No sweethearts.
[sighs]
I like horses.
Ah. You're a homely
but passionate man.
So my guess is,
your heart was broken
by a beautiful but cruel
and faithless woman.
30 years ago.
What the hell's that got
to do with this girl?
Probably nothing.
What's your position
on the increased ferry service?
[chuckles]
You're pokin'
at me again, huh?
I'll tell you my position.
Of course, we need
more ferry service.
These islanders got
no business sense at all.
Not even Jack Lafleur?
He struck me as someone that
knows how to do business.
[chuckles]
Oh, he did, did he?
Mr. Stack.
Don't mind my asking, but where
were you the night before last?
Just like always,
right here.
Is there anyone
who can verify that?
Sure. My ranch hands.
Can we talk to them?
Sure, you can.
They're in the corral.
Jane, we'd better--
Why don't you lead the way,
Mr. Stack?
[sighs]
Watch he doesn't kick.
What happened to you?
Horse did.
Oh.
We were culling steer.
Had about 40 head of cattle.
39 head.
- I said "about."
- No such thing as "about."
Either you got 40 head,
or you got 39 head.
Whit would correct the good lord
if he got the count wrong.
We were taking 'em up
to the south pasture.
One got spooked, went over
the side, and took me with it.
I don't know what made
Whit holler more.
A horse rolling over him or
going to the mainland to set it.
- Shut up.
- You don't like the mainland?
Or you don't like
the ferryboat ride?
Neither. I like it here.
Why?
It's quiet.
Yeah.
Seems, uh, old man Stack
feels the same way, huh?
Listen, between you and me...
this whole cowboy thing is
an act with Stack, isn't it?
I mean, he's all hat
and, uh, no stirrups,
as you say?
It's all hat
and no cattle.
- What-what is it?
- All hat and no cattle.
That's what you call
a man like that.
[Jed]
'A man like what?'
Oh, I was just asking about
old, uh, cowboy sayings.
Whit was just correcting him.
Weren't you, whit?
If you'll excuse me,
I gotta take care
of something in the barn.
Sure. Thanks, whit.
Fella's a bit shy,
but, uh, he's a good worker.
- I'd like to interview him.
- No need, Lisbon.
I've already spoken to, uh,
Mr. Stack's workforce here.
We should leave. Thank you.
Where were the three of you
the night before last?
Here. Like always.
Okay. We can go now.
Thank you for your time.
We'll be in touch.
[cell phone rings]
Lisbon.
We got a break
in the case.
A series of incoming calls
to Talia Suarez's motel.
All from a cell phone registered
to a guy named Dennis Kagan.
Who's Dennis Kagan?
'An ex-foster kid who shared'
a couple of group homes
with Talia.
The last call came within a
10-mile radius of Talia's motel.
'Sounds interesting.'
Yeah, especially since
Kagan lives
100 miles Southwest
of the motel.
Are we bringing him in?
Van Pelt and Cho are gonna
pick him up right now.
This is the address.
Apartment's
on the second floor.
- You get a picture of Kagan?
- Yeah, from the DMV.
Here.
'That's him.'
Yeah.
Okay. Let's go.
I'll take lead.
Got it.
Hey. Dennis, right?
You Dennis Kagan?
Maybe.
You're friends
with Talia Suarez, right?
I don't know the name, man.
Keep walkin'.
- I think you do know.
- Hey, get off me, bitch.
Stay right there.
- You're under arrest.
- Uhh!
Put your hands
behind your back...
Get off.
O-okay. I'll take it from here.
Come on. Come on.
[sighs]
It'd be better for you
if you talked to me, Dennis.
You're already looking
at assaulting a police officer.
Don't make it harder
on yourself.
Look, I told you
I want a lawyer.
One's on the way from
the Public Defender's office.
I just wanna give you
a chance to work with us.
Earn yourself
some goodwill.
Hey, it's up to you
how you want to play it.
A lawyer, that's how.
Alright.
Have it your way.
[elevator bell dings]
Hi. You must be from
the public defenders office.
I'm agent Grace Van Pelt.
Grace. Oh. Hi. Right.
Nice to meet you.
I'm Sarah Harrigan.
- Do we know each other?
- No. Um, I j--
Last year there was
a murder at a dating service
and you guys
interviewed me.
Don't worry.
I didn't do it.
[laughing]
Hey, Cho. This is Sarah Harrigan
from the Public Defender's
office.
- Hey.
- Hello, Agent..
Hey, guys. I can handle this.
Sarah, let me bring you
to your client.
- Did that feel weird to you?
- Yeah, a little bit.
Really? What was that all about?
Well, it seems obvious.
They're dating.
So, Dennis,
you've got your lawyer.
- Let's talk.
- I've spoken with my client.
He's willing to help you,
with some stipulations.
We're not making any deals.
[Sarah]
'Go ahead.'
Look, Talia was looking
for the guy
that killed her dad.
'Cause the damn cops
didn't do their job.
My client is speaking
from a place of emotion.
- Means no disrespect.
- They didn't.
They knew who did the murder
and they never bothered
to find him.
And this suspect..
You ever hear his name?
Uh..
...I'm trying to remember.
[sighing]
A funny name
like, uh, Tommy Tuna
or something like that.
[sighing]
Fish?
Yeah. That's the guy.
Uh, Edward Fish.
It was Edward Fish. Yeah.
So you went to her motel.
Why?
[sighing]
'Cause I wanted
to stop her, you know?
Look, what Talia was doing
was dangerous, okay?
She liked to act tough,
but she wasn't, really.
She had my back
in the homes.
I should have had hers..
...but I was too late.
There you are.
Oh, thank you very much.
That looks delicious.
Did you make that?
Mm-hmm.
What do you know about this,
uh, rancher, Stack?
They keep to themselves,
mostly.
He seems like a polite man.
That's delicious.
I thought about
what you said this morning.
You made me feel rather guilty
about that poor girl.
Oh. I'm-I'm sorry. I don't want
anyone to feel guilty
unless, of course,
they are.
Are you?
[chuckling]
Oh, no.
No. I thought not.
I threw a flower
into the ocean for her.
You did?
It's an old island custom.
'My mother said
it sent a message'
to your people
who had passed over.
I mean, I know
the girl isn't my family
but I think it'll
still work, don't you?
Well, it can't hurt.
[chuckling]
You think
I'm a foolish old woman
but I'll tell you this.
[cellphone ringing]
I feel better.
[ringing continues]
I feel like I did..
...something to give
that girl some peace.
[ringing continues]
Lisbon, you're calling
to tell me that
the, uh, person of interest
you're following
is not the murderer.
No, but he told us
what Talia was looking for.
Oh?
She was looking for her father's
murderer, Edward Fish.
Hmm.
'Yeah, you'd better
get back here.'
Excuse me, Agent Lisbon.
A word?
- Uh..
- Hmm.
You sound busy, Lisbon,
so don't worry about me.
I know exactly what to do.
Bye.
[sighing]
[receiver clattering]
Yes, counselor?
Yeah,
my client Dennis Kagan..
You are dropping
all charges, I assume
since he's been
such a cooperative witness?
And I've got an agent
with cuts and bruises
as a result
of your client.
And I've got assault
failure to identify,
and excessive force.
Do we really want
to go there
given where your guys
have been already?
It'll never hold up in court,
and you know it, but okay.
Oh, fantastic.
You're meaner
than you look.
Yeah, you are.
[chuckling]
Oh, I try.
- We're still on for tonight?
- Oh, yeah. Sure. Okay.
I'm gonna research
the dad's murder.
Good idea.
[telephone rings,
police radio chatter]
[ring]
hey, boss.
I just made a new pot.
You want a cup?
No.
It's funny
you should mention coffee
because I got off the phone
with a social worker
who claims one of my agents
threw a cup of it at her.
What? It spilled on her desk
as we were leaving.
Didn't even get on her.
Sure you don't want any?
Tell me what's going on
whether or not I can
count on you.
Of course you can.
Why would you even ask me that?
Because right before I spoke
to the social worker
a lawyer from
the public defenders office
threatened to bring you up
on charges of excessive force.
- I'd to cut her client loose.
- You did what?
I'm the one with the busted lip.
He didn't have a mark.
You didn't touch him?
Boss, come on.
So you're telling me that
even though I've gotten
two complaints about you
within the space of an hour
that there's nothing
going on?
You're fine?
Yeah, that's what
I'm saying.
Okay. Look, I know
it's been a tough year.
We've got a new boss.
We're under a lot of scrutiny.
It's really important that
we make a good impression.
- Do you understand?
- I didn't do anything wrong.
Grace.
As a friend, should I be
worried about you?
I'm fine.
The social worker's
just pissed off
that somebody was trying
to make her do her job
and the kid got
out of line.
It's not a big deal.
- The lawyer'd have had no case.
- Alright.
Well, as your boss,
any more of this
and we've got
a serious problem.
Got it.
[police radio chatter]
[birds chirping]
Hi.
Hello.
Mr. Jane, right?
That's right.
Wow. This place is amazing.
Did you do this all yourself?
No. The monarchs do
most of it.
I just try to make their journey
a little easier.
And that's, uh, because insects
deserve a better life?
I know. It's a foolish
obsession, isn't it?
I often wonder..
...why I do it,
but here I am.
Here you are.
But if the cruise ships make
this island a port of call
'this could be a wonderful
tourist attraction.'
You could make yourself
a lot of money.
Cruise ships?
What are you talking about?
Oh, Jack Lafleur..
Do you know him?
The fisherman, yeah.
Yeah, well, apparently
he's, uh, rebuilding his jetty
into, uh, a pier or a wharf,
whichever's bigger.
Why would he do that?
Where'd he get the money?
Well,
I'm not entirely sure
but, uh, I think the money's
coming from stack.
I think the idea is to lure
cruise ships, uh, to the island.
Oh, my god.
I have to make some calls
to the coastal commission.
Um, there's gotta be a way
to stop this.
I suggest the, uh,
Sierra Club, too.
[knock on door]
What's up?
Winston Suarez..
Talia's dad.
Worked as a night guard
in a construction business
near Modesto
and this is the guy
who killed him..
...Edward William Fish,
A.K.A. Eddy Fish.
Nothing to do
with Jack Lafleur.
So Talia went to go
and find Fish
and he killed her
when she did?
Uh, what about the rape?
Does that fit in with his MO?
Fish was a crackhead who stabbed
Winston Suarez 18 times
when he tried to stop Fish
from robbing
the construction company.
That's a lot of blood.
Fish disappeared
with over 300 grand.
Cops never found him.
Assumption is he used the money
to change his appearance
and identity.
What's the connection
to San Felix?
Talia found
the case file.
San Felix's mentioned
as an early lead.
Alright. Thanks.
- Jane.
- 'Hey, Lisbon.'
I'm just putting some of the
finishing touches in place.
'You be careful.'
This Eddy Fish
is a dangerous man.
He stabbed Talia's father
18 times.
It's a good thing
we're about to catch him.
Let's not get ahead
of ourselves.
[chuckling]
If he's on this island, Lisbon
he will reveal
himself to us.
Hang on.
Interesting, huh, guys?
Oh, did...did you hear
about what's happening
with Stack and Gardiner?
What?
Stack has been working
with Lafleur
to try to bring cruise ships
into the harbor.
- Cruise ships?
- Here?
Yeah, and then Gardiner
found out
and he's vowed to stop it
immediately.
What?
We've got to call
a town meeting right away.
Better hurry, Lisbon.
You'll miss all the fun.
I've practically got
the killer in handcuffs.
[indistinct conversation]
[Jack]
What business does anybody
have to do with my dock?
Well, now as a community,
it's everyone's concern..
I-I know this island's
a jewel in the rough.
I'm just lookin'
to polish it up.
No, listen,
the environmental danger
of ferry service pales in
comparison to cruise ships!
The chair has not recognized
Mr. Gardiner.
[Patrick]
Ladies and gentlemen,
sorry for the interruption.
'This is a top priority.'
I'm here with the CBI.
It's okay.
Everything is completely
under control.
I'm gonna need you to follow
my instructions to the letter.
Listen to everything I say
very carefully.
The first thing I need you to do
is to place your coffee cups
on those two tables
back there.
All of you, your coffee cups
on the table back there.
[singsong voice]
For this to work
you're gonna have to listen
and do as you're told.
[normal voice]
Thank you.
Your coffee cups on the table.
This is a serious matter.
[indistinct conversation]
'You too, please.
Thank you.'
'And then return
to your seats..'
...as quickly
and efficiently..
...as you can.
'Thank you.'
Okay. That wasn't so bad.
We've tracked the killer
to this island.
[woman #1]
'The killer's here?'
Yes.
He's here in this room
right now.
His name is Eddy Fish.
[crowd murmuring]
I don't know which one
of you that is
but you killed
Talia Suarez's father.
That's why she came here..
To find you.
Now I'm here..
'...to finish off
what Talia started.'
'Yes.'
[clearing throat]
To catch Eddy Fish.
- What are you going to do?
- Me?
Nothing.
It's already done.
The fingerprints on the cups..
[man #1]
What? No way.
...match them
to the original crime scene.
[indistinct conversation]
- Is that legal?
- N-no, I want my cup back.
Don't worry. I'm gonna get
a camera to document
everything they're doing.
We have rights.
I don't know why you're
all getting so worked up.
Only one of you is guilty.
The rest of you should
just sit back, relax
'have another piece of cake.'
Am I the only one thinking
that's the last
we'll see of Mr. Gardiner?
[starting motor]
You going somewhere,
Mr. Gardiner?
[grunting]
Aah!
No! Let go of me!
I'll kill you!
[grunting]
Eddy Fish, you're under
arrest for the murders
of Winston Suarez
and Talia Suarez.
[grunting and panting]
You've the right
to remain silent.
Anything you say can be used
against you in a court of law.
You've the right
to speak to an attorney.
If you cannot afford
an attorney
one will be appointed
to you.
I didn't know who she was.
I didn't kill her!
I never even saw the girl.
I didn't know
she was on the island.
[indistinct conversation]
Who'd have thought?
He always seemed like
such a nice man.
Mm. He did, didn't he?
Boat's heading over
to transport us back now.
I'm gonna find someplace
to hold the prisoner.
Good idea.
Tell Cho and Van Pelt.
Okay.
Well, we do thank you, ma'am.
That was some nice work
you all did.
Thank you, Mr. Stack.
Just doing our job.
I did wonder about the man.
It was a feeling I had.
I don't know
what it was exactly
but, uh, normal people
don't feed crickets.
Butterflies.
Whatever. Bugs.
The point is,
I got instincts about people.
[Patrick laughing]
No, you don't.
You were fooled,
just like everybody else.
You callin' me a liar?
No, it's only that
now you know him
as Eddy Fish,
the violent sociopath.
It's easy for you
to see him as a killer.
But as the shy lepidopterist,
Gardiner?
Impossible for anyone to imagine
him stabbing a man 14 times.
- Eighteen times.
- Right. 18. 18 times.
Unimaginable, and a number
that you can't forget
once you've heard it.
'Eighteen times.'
Where did you hear it
exactly?
What? Oh, uh, from you,
uh, earlier.
No, not from me.
Where then?
I-I don't...I don't know
what you're talking about.
Gardiner killed
Talia's father.
That's true, but, uh,
he didn't kill Talia.
Well, he might have
'if he'd known she was here
looking for him'
'but he wouldn't have
raped her.'
No, not his thing.
You did it.
'You met her on the ferryboat
coming back from the hospital.'
[chuckling]
What? No.
Wow. You say no,
but your eyes tell me yes.
[Terence]
Talia asked for your help.
She told you about
her father and Fish
and the 18 stab wounds.
That's how you got that
scratch on your face.
You're strong enough to hold
a girl down single-handed
but you couldn't protect
your face.
Gardiner killed her.
We all saw.
No.
You're wrong.
Doubtful.
Proving it should
be easy, though
since you gave us
your DNA to match.
Cuff him, Lisbon.
[motor rumbling]
Does it make you
uncomfortable, Mr. Naylor
being alone here with me?
It should.
I'd gladly hurt you for
what did to that poor girl
hurt you badly.
Whoa, agent.
Cool it down, okay?
It's not his fault
what happened.
Oh, please.
It's not his fault?
No.
You're a decent guy.
I can tell.
If you could have
controlled yourself
you would have, right?
You don't want to hurt anyone.
- No.
When you get those urges,
it's-it's like somebody else
taking over your body, right?
Somebody evil?
Yeah.
[scoffing]
Come on.
No, really.
[box scraping floor]
Listen..
...I understand that you were
trying to control yourself.
That's why you went
to Stack's ranch on San Felix..
...to take yourself away
somewhere safe
somewhere away
from temptation, right?
But then you hurt
your shoulder
and a doctor needed
to set it
and there's no doctor
on the island.
I wanted to stay
on the ranch.
I didn't..
I didn't want to leave.
And she was on the ferry
coming back, wasn't she?
She asked about your arm.
She came to me.
She asked for my help
wanted me to hide her.
Yeah, so you took her
to the ranch.
An outbuilding..
...where nobody goes.
Where no one would hear
when you raped and killed her.
You can't judge me.
You don't know
what it's like to be me.
You think I want to be
like this?
You have the gall to ask
for pity after what you've done?
You'll get no pity
not in this life
or the next.
[sighing]
Nice work back there.
Thanks. You too.
Yeah, we really had him
fooled, huh?
He thought you were
a real hard case.
[chuckling]
Yeah.
Listen, about before
at the office with Sarah
I just want to..
Oh, yeah. Congratulations.
She seems nice.
Yeah, I just don't want it
to be awkward between..
[laughing]
With me?
That's the least
of your problems.
What does that mean?
Well,
she's a public defender.
I mean, good luck,
but be careful.
[Lisbon]
'Hey. The boat's docking now.'
Get the prisoners
and get 'em on board.
- Yeah. Sure thing, boss.
- Have you seen Jane?
- No.
Better get here quick,
or he's gonna get left behind.
[sighing]
[theme music]